Bob Montana Cartoons
Bob Montana Cartoons
1946-1970
Montana, Bob
12 linear ft.
Original daily and Sunday cartoons from the newspaper comic strip version of Archie.
149319
Biographical History
Bob Montana (1920-1975) was born in Stockton, California to a vaudeville family. A self-described "art school dropout" from the Boston Museum, the Phoenix Institute and the Art Students League of New York, he is best known as the creator of the popular comic character Archie. His other cartoons include Danny in Wonderland, Inspector Bentley, Lu-Nar, and Spark Stevens. He also created cover art during World War II for Pep, Zip, Top-Notch, and Jackpot, frequently depicting superheroes such as The Shield, Steel Sterling, and the Black Hood battling Japanese and Nazi soldiers.
Archie debuted in Pep and Jackpot in 1941 and got his first solo comic book in 1942 but was put on hold for four years when Montana joined the Army Signal Corps where he worked on training films with fellow cartoonists Sam Cobean and Charles Addams. After leaving the army, Montana started the Archie newspaper strip, which ran in both daily and Sunday versions. Since Montana did not own the character, other artists also drew the red-headed teenager, but Montana remained with the strip until his death.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Bob Montana Cartoons collection consists of 1,537 original daily cartoons and 183 original Sunday cartoons from the newspaper comic strip version of Archie. Daily cartoon: traces of graphite, zipatone, brush, pen and ink on illustration board, approx. 7 ¼ x 23 in. Sunday cartoon: traces of graphite, blue pencil, paste-overs, brush, pen and ink on illustration board, approx. 15 ¼ x 22 in.
Arrangement of the Collection
Daily and Sunday cartoons are arranged separately in chronological order.
Related Material
has collections of over one hundred cartoonists. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Montana, Bob.; Archie (comic strip); Art -- Cartoonists; American wit and humor, Pictorial.; Andrews, Archie (Fictitious character); Caricatures and cartoons -- United States.; Cartoonists -- United States.; Comic books, strips, etc. -- United States.; Cartoons (humorous images); Cartoonists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Bob Montana, 1970.
Inventory
- Archie comic strip
  Click here for detailed inventory.
  - Daily cartoons, 1,537
    - 1946 Mar - 1949 Jun (Box 1)
    - 1949 Jul - 1951 Jun (Box 2)
    - 1951 Jul - 1954 Jan (Box 3)
    - 1954 Feb - 1955 Jun (Box 4)
    - 1955 Jul - 1956 Dec (Box 5)
    - 1957 May - 1957 Dec (Box 6)
    - 1958 Jan - 1961 Oct (Box 7)
    - 1962, 1965, 1967 (Box 8)
    - 1968 Jan - 1969 May (Box 9)
  - Sunday cartoons
    - 1956 Jan - 1970 Jan (Oversize 1)